software engineering radio episode 73
real-time systems with Bruce Powell
Douglas
[Music]
Oh welcome listeners to a new episode of
software engineering radio this is
another episode in our series on
embedded software development and this
time we're talking to Bruce Powell
Douglas the chief scientists and
whatever that means he'll explain it in
a minute of teller logic so Bruce
welcome to the show
thanks for agreeing to to join the
podcast so why don't we start by having
you introduce yourself and your personal
background your professional background
a little bit so people know who you are
all right well let's see I was raised by
wolves in the wilds of Oregon I taught
myself to read when I was three Java
self calculus when I was twelve quit
school when I was 14 and went to college
I currently got three degrees master's
bachelor's and a doctorate by doctors
and neural cybernetics which is the
study of information processing Indian
biological neural systems I've been
involved in software for a long time now
ran my own software company doing in
statistical numerical analysis and
various kind of lab embedded work I've
been involved in various kinds of safety
critical business of us for the last 20
odd 25 years everything from medical
systems to fire control systems aircraft
designs and both of a systems side and
for the software side for the last 11
years I've been working with AI logics
and now internal logic as a chief
evangelist doing I guess some product
visionary work for the Rhapsody tool
doing some standards work I'm one of the
authors of the contributing to the UML
standard the upm unified profile for
dota wrote a standard you know profile
for risk is ability performance and time
as well as other standards and I also do
a lot of consulting in the real time
that it
marketplace all over the world in Turkey
in Europe in Asia in the US and Canada
and so on
aren't you an IBM employee now I heard
rumors that teleological was was bought
by IBM IBM has issued an offer but at
the present time the offer is not yet
done there are some conditions as to the
number of percentage of of proxies they
can purchase and so on this is expected
to be resolved by end of this month and
then if it goes forward the sale would
probably take place in September of this
year ok but let's not let's not talk
about these kinds of things let's let's
get to the meat which is real-time
systems so why don't we start by you
explaining a little bit what a real-time
system is and what some of the well
distinguishing properties of these kinds
of systems are all right well the most
important aspect of real time means that
time is essential for correctness now
one of the ways that people model time
is deadlines and that's that's really
the most common way but really is just a
subset of the overall real-time systems
development and again set of concepts
the cool aspect of real times it's just
that time is essential for correctness
and within that context there are things
like hard real-time systems are usually
model that could deadlines there are
soft real-time systems will you model
things as over some stochastic measure
of timeliness such as minimizing mean
lateness for example doing average
throughput average batteries for the
still considered real-time but time is
an essential correctness is the
essential characteristic of a real-time
system and then the the level to which
timeliness is important like whether one
missed deadline is already a failure or
whether that's just well a problem that
can be fixed with with subsequent well
cycles that depends on a specific kind
of system you build right an action is
said to have a deadline in the common
with Marlin
but what it is it's really a
simplification and again this
implication is what people do that is
because the math of eating okay there's
of a step function and against deadlines
it's called utility function in general
it is the value of the copy of the
completion of the computation over time
yes that value goes from infinity
infinity or one depending upon how you
wanna model out there to zero it's an
instant time that incident time is
called the deadline but actual fact in
general there is in there might be a
decreasing value decreasing utility
function which may not just be a cell
phone so you're saying it might be if
it's a little bit late that's not quite
as good but it's not necessarily a fatal
failure which case is not a it's not
really a deadline kind of driven system
but people did lines to model it because
right yeah and and another thing you
already mention is responsiveness that's
that that goes to the average throughput
I guess that means for example a system
can take whatever 1,000 measurements per
second but it doesn't really matter if a
specific measurement point in time moves
by a microsecond for before for aback
especially true in baby even unimportant
whether or not he did all the
measurements for example it may be able
to have one be late you may be able to
drop it all together depends on the
nature of the system there's a saying
that hard little times are hard but soft
little times are harder right and again
it's harder just because the math is
hard of massive more complex to
determine whether or not you're an
adequate throughput mm-hmm that's
actually a good point never looked at
this this way I always thought that more
or less hard deadlines hard real-time is
the real challenge but right well chalk
11 of my book doing a hard time goes
into this concept in some detail mm-hmm
actually the good point we should point
people to the book and put that into the
show notes book is also basically that
the kind of the basis that I use for
coming up with some of the questions so
something that's related to being able
to meeting deadlines I guess is the idea
of being able to schedule a system in a
way that is actually more or less
provable or well at least it's like
that the system as its scheduled is able
to meet the deadlines right well there
are many ways to discuss there are two
primary taxonomy I guess one are
fairness doctrines
where everybody gets a chance to play
and one our priority scheme is where
we're trying to ensure that important
things happen in the tailing way and
systems are often built with either or
on an often build with both features
kind of in place on some aspects of
fairness and some aspects of real time
this the most common way to schedule
well I guess it depends on is the main
the most common way to schedules
near-vertical avionics is with the
cyclic executive even though it's de
menthe ELISA optimal in terms of
performance it's very very simple so
it's very predictable but in other
environments the most common way to
schedule and for hard real-time systems
is to use priority based preemption and
within that the most common approach is
RMA rate monotonic analysis lead
monotonic scheduling and in that if you
make the assumption that the deadline
occurs at the end of the period and your
periodic I've been arrivals yeah and you
schedule them such that the higher the
short of the timeframe become the period
the harder the priority and it's an it's
an optimal schema it's also stable but
optimal we means that if that task set
can be scheduled by any means it can
also be scheduled by RMS and it's stable
in the sense that in an overload
situation where you can't meet your
deadlines you can predict ahead of time
which tasks fulfill there will be the
little priority tab yep so it's up to
the application developer to make the
non important things the tasks with a
well obviously with lots of high
priority right in my book real time
design patterns I devote a chapter or
two to the aspects of you know
concurrency and selection of scheduling
patterns also sharing the resources
across concurrency unit batters and that
sort of thing this is a there's a lot of
literature out there on on better ways
to do this but ultimately yes
developer needs to select a design a
pattern design solution that this meets
the semantic needs of the application
know if you do a cyclic scheduling then
you obviously have to know first of all
the the well the worst the longest
execution time of each of the tasks you
run in that cycle and also you need to
know the typical or average or worst
case load I guess so predicting the load
that the system will will have to deal
with is probably a very important aspect
of building a real world real time
system
well no specific executives aren't very
efficient because if I've got to see a
set of ten tasks and again comes in that
needs to be consumed by the tenth task
and I'm not on task one it has to wait
until that tenth tax gets around
executing before can handle that event
and in many systems that's too late in
which case you might want to go to a
priority based preemption schema there's
a very famous case of the busy one
submarine simulator which the the
originator and it would run for a few
minutes and then it would just crash and
his hang and so they try changing it all
to assembly code and that de noir they
brought in some guys from the sei and
analyzed it and they said what you need
to do is rather than sicker executive
his party basis schema and he's learned
that scheduling and then it just ran so
he did that and the original a giraffe
it wasn't the execution time of the
assembly code that was the issue it was
really the ordering of priorities of the
events coming in so we talked already
about task priorities there is other
terms arrived that I've read and
actually I don't really know how they
exactly relate these are urgency and
importance with Empire schemas there are
two primary scheduling sub schemas if
you will urgency and importance urgency
you think about utility function okay
urgency is the link and before the
deadline occurs so it's a measure of the
newness of the deadline so something
that near in time is urgent something as
far in time is not urgent in terms of
the importance importance
height of that utility function so
something that's important is it's a
higher function might be value can with
something less important might be value
one you can you the schedule based on
urgency or you can schedule based on
criticality so what you're saying is if
something is not very important but
urgent and something else is very
important but not yet so urgent you
might still decide to do the important
thing first
suppose you're flying a jet plane and
you have to flow your control services
every 50 milliseconds yeah or the plane
because unstable and bad things happen
yeah okay that has a certain urgency and
of course obviously very high importance
yeah on the other hand suppose you're
watching the movie loss in translation
on the DVD player in the cockpit of your
jet fighter okay that has a frame update
rate that has to occur every 10
milliseconds that is more urgent than
controlling these big wing services of
the aircraft but hardly particularly
that movie hardly important yeah okay
yeah see the point so urgent and
importance of two criteria that
determine the priority and actually I
think that's what you said before right
an RMS for example is is a fundamentally
urgency a schema so predictability I
guess we talked about is an important
characteristic we want to predict how
many whatever measurements you can do
you want to predict how long something's
gonna take you probably also want to
predict the resources you wanna use for
these tasks because otherwise probably
your system will have to acquire
resources as it runs and that makes it
unpredictable with regards to time right
oh absolutely and ability can be very
conservative very problematic depends on
the flexibility the system release to
release flexible systems are the most
predictable right because we don't have
to respond to somebody changing demands
the most flexible ones are the most
difficult yeah so for this reason what
many people do video what's called
worst-case analysis they see in the
woods case I'll get events coming at
this rate for this lawn with this kind
of a burst length and I have to handle
this this many messages for so long and
there's a number of ways
this case it can be for example if
things are a periodic for example they
occur when the car somebody's typing on
a keyboard what you would do in terms of
which case analysis you say well what's
the fastest time this person can type on
the keyboard well okay that's that's 40
milliseconds pinkie presses this is like
a monster a typist you can just can
boost out certain lawyers because it's
not them kind of like memory coded
however most of this typing will be much
much lower than that in might be a
verage 500 milliseconds alright but
because you're doing worst-case analysis
you simplify assume that this is
periodic at the rate of 40 milliseconds
I'll know I meet my deadlines since we
don't know which keeps analysis what
often happens is I over design the
systems which I wear but that they we
filter they get more reliable systems
because if that were occurring for cool
I can go handle it sure yeah but then of
course wastes resources if you so if you
have to handle many whatever sessions or
many channels at the same time and you
plan for each each with the worst case
then you obviously waste resources but
that's the price you pay I guess yes
sometimes you can if you can relax with
these assumptions you can clearly
decrease the price of assistance I mean
the FDA yeah so if they had a since
they're kind of replace the air traffic
control system two years back yeah and
he wanted me you know 7/9 of the
liability yeah
and they failed they stand to let three
billion dollars and failed because they
had all that specify the system they
could lead yeah so so another thing that
comes to mind here is of course then
also graceful degradation I mean at some
point the system needs to detect that
the that the load is actually higher
than it was designed for and then do
something that is not crashing I guess
well those we call the defensive design
you have expectations about the rain and
valuables variables of the arrival times
of the events and so on and when you do
defensive development as well as the
sense of testing you test boundary
conditions around that range as well as
some things that shouldn't a principal
courage just to make sure that for
whatever reason if the assumptions are
wrong or the environment changed that
you still don't do the wrong thing maybe
the right thing is
anyway maybe it's causing arre sad to me
that's resetting the first time yeah
maybe it's not a fine either but making
sure that the right thing happens at all
the right time this is crucial for high
reliability systems which is you know
particle systems leaving our control and
it's also that leads into the topic of
fault tolerance and fault media fault
mitigation and that's something we're
going to talk about actually soon with
Bob Henry who's writing another book on
this topic so this goes together quite
well so let's look at the maybe main
architectural styles for building
real-time systems you already touched on
these things event based versus time
trigger can you maybe give a small
concise definition of what the
difference is between these two systems
and where they are used
well the harming process which is the
process that I developed and if the the
process used in consulting from tell
logic in running process there are five
really fundamental views of architecture
and then maybe a few other ones
depending upon particular circumstances
but the five phenomenal ones are the
subsystem component architecture which
are the large-scale pieces of the system
the subsystems are components whether
you want to call them they're their
interfaces and their responsibilities
the second is the distribution
architecture which is how these elements
are distributed across multiple address
spaces how they find each other the
communicate reliably and how they
collaborate next we have the concurrency
and resource management architecture
which is the identification of the tasks
Fred's the conversing units how they're
scheduled how they share resources and
how they're invented properties are
characterized next we have the safety
and reliability architecture which is
how we identify isolate and correct
faults at runtime using for the means of
design patterns and redundancy of the
architectural level and lastly we have
the distribution architecture I'm sorry
the deployment architecture notice how
the different engineering disciplines
such as software electronics mechanical
chemical
whatever work together in the system
what the interfaces are with
responsibilities are and so on
so we view in our new process
architecture as one or more design
decisions design patterns in each one of
these different architectural areas
the question was reactive or event based
system versus time triggered systems
probably wrong to call these
architectures but they are well the way
the systems execute is probably are
usually concerned primarily periodically
based right so that is the event arrival
pattern for the advantages periodic and
there's some variation on the period
called computer and based on that you
can assign your priorities using means
such as early at deadlines first rate
monotonic scheduling or whatever to
achieve the scalability particularly of
the outcome the events driven over the
called a periodic or permanent a
periodic events and these advance a
curve when they curve one of these in
size did something when an event in the
universe of interest happens and so
these systems are actually lots of times
modeled as periodic with the worst case
and the minimum into arrival time those
events model of the period and that way
even though you were design the system
you were robust against conditions that
may really occur another way there can
model air pure existence is to look at
even if they can come instantly fast
they don't come from they long any
system with the events come infinitely
fast infinitely long you can't meet
those deadlines okay cannot be done so
he has to somehow bound it and so
another way to found the problem is you
might have a burst length which is a
known fixed length you might have like
an infinitely fast but they might only
be a burst of 100 right and so you have
some limit to that and then there's some
rest interval between that burst and
then you can analyze you need two
categories like Markov chains queueing
theory and so on to analyze the system
for scalability particularly so is that
something that's done typically in
practice that you really analyze and
simulate a system or is it more like
let's build something and then let's try
whether it work so what's the what's the
best practice or does this depend on the
safety issues there this practice is to
do the analysis however I think it is
where the most common engineering
approach is prayer to say oh god I hope
this works rather than do the analysis
and I think that that's unfortunate
because there are tools out there across
Pacific for example as a tool called
rapid RMA they can do some stochastic as
well as are any kind of analysis so
their tool that they're going to help
you analyze it another standard called
you know profile this gives ability
performance in time which identifies a
set of take values metadata like
priority list case execution time
walking time and so on that you can use
to change your elements with and uni and
ull speaking and then these tools can
read URL because there's no this define
standard I can read it for some with the
XML I analyze the model and then say
whether or not you can always meet your
deadlines or what you might have to do
to ensure that you could always meet
your deadline I mean probably the DH
it's the same problem everywhere that if
you want to do simulation analysis then
your models have to be formal correct
and complete and that's probably not
many people actually want to do this so
they probably just hacked together
something and then try well yeah well
[Music]
I'm a big believer in using UML in an
executable way all the way through
development is very kind of an agile
approach that the point in which we're
doing continual excuses a-fightin from
working on system for example I'm
helping to architect a helicopter design
in Canada right now when I architected
system work on a system I build it as a
piece of incrementally executable model
so even if the outset I had something a
day one I have something that runs yeah
and it has a very specific purpose and
this model then evolves over time and
then always run daily I'm running the
systems you know it's 10 times 20 times
a day
well so I can always do the kind of
execution but you're right in terms of
doing some analysis we have if you look
in the book by any other name right now
these practitioners guide to digital
analysis by clear press and if then it's
kind of the Bible for for reading
monotonic in a linear thinking of a
number of different ways number of
different techniques to analyze systems
whether they have stochastic properties
whether they re gender than a time
driven so there's a number of different
ways you can analyze the data and you
can do this what's called global RMA
analysis so you just identify your task
threads and some of the resources you
know the blocking times are in a very
high level do some quick analysis but
but then over time you if you'll evolve
these models you can have more more
fidelity in detail and get better
answers I think the time to find out
that you missed your deadlines is not
when the plane is in flight ok
the time to find this out is before the
plane of even on the tarmac and I do
that you have to do really executions so
are in the hungry process what we do is
we do based on the use case analysis for
the functionality is applying the
quality of service we determine the
overall performance budgets so I have to
do my control surface you know
fluttering within 50 milliseconds of the
planes unstable okay then I identify
inside the aircraft the chain of
elements that have to work together to
do that and each one of them gets a
piece of that performance budget and
it's unit tested against that part of
its performance budget such that when it
comes back if it needs a performance
which I know the entire chain will work
and it earlier you do this the better
off you are
it's kind of like when you argue with
your wife okay if you wait six weeks to
resolve an argument it's a huge deal
we're talking lawyers right it's a major
major deal if you resolve it that
evening it's quick and easy
that's less pain the longer you wait the
more pain it is so you really want to
make these decisions particularly in an
environment where you expect performance
to be a concern
Louise you can't add track it and
monitor it all the way to development
and it's portable how many process
and and well now that we were talking
about that talking about the modeling
and description of real-time systems you
already mentioned the role of UML so I
guess these days there aren't any other
formalisms that are used for that kind
of stuff
I remember room roq the kind of guy and
so on it's there they were these notion
of good notion of these capsules and
there are things like structured classes
right under equivalent but really if the
old concept of blocks preceded room and
you can argue entomology which is much
more towards if you know than it would
be towards so so it's STL used much
these days or is it all more or less
subsumed under UML 2.0 you know my
experience there is certainly a
potential accom and particularly in
europe still interest in SPO but it has
been largely replaced by um our
personnel that's my friend ok so which
diagrams of the UML or which well which
which URL subset is particularly useful
for these kinds of sirs well I think you
can build any system with three diagrams
types okay
the other ones do add value and I'm not
saying you shouldn't use them whether
three core essential diagrams you need
you need to have a structural view and
that's provided by class diagrams of
those excellent and UML unfortunately
defined you know class diagrams package
diagrams collection class diagrams as if
they were different yeah they're not
different than theirs the same diagram
it just depends on what your emphasis of
the purpose of the diagram might be now
so class diagrams for the structural
elements and the relations so that's an
important key view for example is how
you do concurrent analysis identify
these active objects they are the units
of concurrency and they contain the
semantic objects from your from your now
as a smaller platform-independent model
as parts make sure the context of that
threat so that's how you do your
constant modeling for example in your
loan okay the second diagram and you
need our state machines because most
these systems are heavily state driven
and state machines Ernest is crucial way
to represent the behavior of such
systems as they receive events change
these and form actions and honestly
sequence diagrams accrue
both in terms of requirement
specification of the system
understanding what you expect the
interaction to be as well as execution
system so using tools like Rhapsody when
you run the system you can dynamically
create sequence diagrams of these
corresponding elements if they
collaborate and then you can compare it
you know mainly you're automatically
with what you expected you could say
haha that's what I expected or huh
wonder why it's doing yeah that's how
would I expected at all yeah three
diagrams I can do so but I always
thought and and probably still think
that sequence diagrams are not that
useful because you cannot describe
closed behavior because they always
design or describe scenarios but if you
use it in the way you just explained by
describing expected scenarios and then
recording the actual behavior and
comparing them then then I guess this
makes quite a lot of sense I didn't
think about that well in case level as
well sort of climbing classes many of
which have state machines you can think
of the sequence diagram as a specific
set of pairs scenario right that's a
scenario and then it is what I really
want to have this why the overall
behavior is every transition and all the
stations in my collaboration is
represented in at least one sequence
diagram and then I have what homie calls
the minimal spanning set yeah that is
all the transitions and all the things
are handled at least once and secrets
diagram so that gives me coverage the
collaboration so it's fair to say that
you use the sequence diagrams to
describe test scenarios or test cases
and then do coverage analysis and
compare it with the running system oh
yeah the controls crucial and the fact
that they have to be if you will
different views another reason want to
have sequence diagrams you know I do a
lot of stuff with the Defense Department
here in the US with regulatory agencies
and government agencies India and Europe
and and different places and there is no
way that you can keep the teacher
typical customer community machine it's
just not gonna happen but in five
minutes I can show them how to read a
sequence paragraph two
we can evaluate the proposed behavior
that's what in fact what they want
yes yeah yeah good very good point down
so so the the stuff we talked about
especially this last one the ability to
illustrate the system's behavior to
let's say well outsiders or non-techies
that's using modeling for documentation
you already mentioned that you use
models to simulate a system and to
analyze properties of the system
how important is cogeneration for these
kinds of things they actually generate
the complete system from these models or
as cogeneration still more or less
unleash these days well I think using
UML or modeling in general for
documentation gives you a very marginal
value for the effort attained I only
strongly fundamentally believe that the
model needs to execute it needs to be
semantic and complete and if it is
semantically complete you can generate
the code yeah my experience I've
consulted
I've got 350 customers different
companies years and over those most of
them almost all of them in fact generate
80% or more of the code from the model
okay so the other they do generate the
code they deploy the code they use that
code in developed systems only a few of
them now a typical system there might be
a little ice driver yes you've already
written it still works there might be a
math library or but you want to use from
somebody else so there's a small amount
of code you don't generate that there is
always a platform against which you
build your system I mean you always
reuse libraries and then stuff you you
wouldn't regenerate them anyway so
that's I think that's trivial that's all
right
but roll in the excess of 80% of the of
the code in a typical system that I
consult on is generated this is true in
helicopter designs include medical
system is it true in telecom systems you
know this is widely true and I think
going through the code base system is
really like going back to a similar
language from speech okay it can be done
but the bottom line is we use modeling
because we can do more in less time with
fewer defects yeah actually I mean I
agree completely I mean I'm working also
in this model driven world not so much
I'm systems but in other kinds of
systems and then well it's exactly my
point why would you write these things
manually but many customers are still
skeptical especially if it's
mission-critical stuff to say well yeah
but we don't really trust the generator
so probably the consequences to improve
the generator as opposed to writing
things manual well what I recommend for
those people and I don't see my fair
share of those people yeah yes that they
should look at the code yeah I mean so
so what we've done sometimes he's gone
and say well we'll go ahead you can do a
something on a write code that's fine
the meantime we still value in just
executing the models I know that your
design is right okay
and well you agree but developing the
coding implementation but as you develop
the code and you review the models here
the code two and see what you think yeah
and so far to a company everyone has
said yeah that's about what I would
write or sometimes it's better than when
I have it right now so it don't depend a
lot of the qualities of cogeneration
there the speed of the model compilers
today is that many of them are really
pretty good of course my first memory
was where I was rhapsody but that but
but there are there are tools out there
I can generate deplorable quality code
in real time in embedded safety-critical
applications so if I want the model to
collude it the complete application that
I also have to model all kinds of
quality of service aspects you already
mentioned this you male profile what is
it scheduled ability and so on you
mentioned before so is that the best
practice way of how to specify timing
resource consumption and other quality
of service aspects right basically you
model in this constraints and they
continue as stereotyped elements they
might take for example an operation and
you said stereotype real-time action and
along with the stereotype you get a tags
values which are places placeholders
metadata like well what is the worst
case execution what is the average
execution time what is the blocking time
and so on so that you can do formal
analysis on that on that model if you
want to do you also do those yeah go
ahead
okay so so that's that's all you kidding
me we represent them typically a result
of a stereotype you get a taste which
are then explained are expressed in
congeal mel constraints to
to take these elements with specific
metadata around their quality service
performance mm-hmm so so you're more
constraints typically just basically
check that a system conforms to certain
properties do you also use constraint
solving as a kind of forward optimizing
a system towards given properties both
constraints or not really imperative
that is a fight if I have an operation
and I give it a constraint of 20
milliseconds I'm not going to generate
different code if I change that
constraint to 15 milliseconds right what
changes is whether or not that code on
the target platform with the target
environment is whether or not so with
both of the constraints are are actually
going to be result in testing conditions
rather than imperative code generation
yeah or watchdog's that stop something
if a time limit is is over right so they
show all these timeouts on a state
machine for good he's a detector certain
timeouts looker but most of them are
testable kinds of things rather than
code degenerative things okay hmm
so you mentioned already the fact that
embedded and real-time systems in
particular aren't software only they you
mentioned the chemical engineers and the
optics and the mechanics and the
electronics and stuff how much you also
mentioned sysml so do these people use
to sum all these days how important this
is ml already in practice we're going to
do a separate episode with I don't know
what the name is the speciality of the
system SS ml team he already agreed but
so what's your experience with Sue's ml
is it already a factor of these days
well we're still actually it's an
adopted standard but not a released
adders okay
listen well let's say it's not actually
officially released its adoptive but now
it's going through what's called a
finalization process where he returned
to 66 nevertheless even though it's not
a released status just an adopted
standard I see it daily we see you know
all kinds of company that won't make any
names but all kinds of earth space
transportation and medical manufacturers
telecom manufacturers using system L in
their daily
work not normally what's done is the
asana and really to be honest so no it's
just you about sure okay with a couple
of smell is just you know there's really
nothing of consequence at it now that
will make some people upset okay
but the major reason personnel became
acceptable system engineers with cozy
named the word class to the word block
that's what made it acceptable okay cuz
it doesn't sound like software stuff
there were a couple of other I want
there are a few things added like
America diagrams I just really usage it
would have a class diagram
they added there were I think an
important additions to activity diagrams
they can then continue sometime as well
as continuous and behavior and then I
think is an important set that should be
folded back into view ml but other than
that we might I think like added like an
allocation dependency and they added a
requirements type but these are really
remember these are just stereotypes
you'll know are since ml is a profile
female which means that they can only in
very minor and well controlled ways
extend the you know and these are very
very minor extensions okay so having
said that since ml is is there's a
standard now it's widely used by system
engineers and of course the most common
you know approach to system engineering
is to use word and bang out exit our
point engineering we call it but
nevertheless those people that are using
that are trying to move up the
abstraction chain to be a little more
precise or adopting v ml in droves every
place I go I pieces about okay different
work cool so now that we talked about
all this modeling stuff let's get a bit
more concrete so what are the languages
programming languages used these days
for building real-time systems this is
still well okay I know that this
question is probably stupid but what
about ADA
I do occasionally although he's more in
Europe and it is interesting I mean it
came from the US yeah mandated standard
own defense that for a number of reasons
one with the compilers or sole expensive
you know $25,000 for compiler was
outrageous when you get a C++ compiler
for 500 I am
and so you had to get an exemption to do
something else and in fact you're really
getting exception so we move the mandate
nevertheless you still see it in Europe
although I have to say it is still if
it's waning its uses waning the most
common language for material
consciousness remains see yep
followed in some environments holding me
closely by C++ a little time Java has
not made a real impact if you see it in
systems where use interface is apparent
concerns people usually like swing and
AWT no libraries for that you can see
that some places like telematics yeah
this was an automotive cinematic things
like that need to see it some but really
if minut market so you use a C++ many
people well some people say that the
plus plus is the problem because it
becomes non deterministic because of all
these virtual function tables is that
really a concern or do you limit
yourself and using C++ to make this a
non-issue well yeah the virtual function
table does not mean it's not predictable
alright because all that is the index
offset addressing the undercoating
something language to look it means that
I'm going to use incremental add to the
accumulator offset addressing defined
neoman right and that's an fixed plane
frame so it doesn't gather detract from
the from the predictability and so why
can't if you took these all these
functions but if statement if this is
truly just this block of this exam the
sort of the block right so in terms of
predictability
that's not an issue the only place where
it is an issue is in the deal when
thinking it being standard they because
it's a very kind of paper heavy standard
it's very about kind of static desk
checking analysis rather than testing
rather than a kind of more modern
analysis because of that it's fairly
difficult to get things a little
function tables approved most people
abandoned the virtual functions when
they're going to use C++ or do you see
for particulars a little a and level B
certification now there is a news
pattern
meeting coming up in September I think
and Russell's for the deal would seem
easy standard which is not something
offer another year or more change yet
but supposedly that standard is going to
be much more object friendly some you
know I think with where software
engineering is in terms of deal with NDB
standard is about 1982 and there's been
some advances and this is the very very
conservative community it's just not a
bad thing
and I want to point out man dancing when
I have to fly on the plane yeah but it
was a conservative community and so they
are slowly adopting and hopefully we'll
get them into the late 80s in this new
standard to see there is you know
cognizant of adjourn annotation and Ken
capsulation encapsulation and deal with
NDB is kind of a bad thing right and so
all of the the current best practices in
terms of social engineering or not
exactly prohibited by the deal once
maybe standard that but they're not
exactly recommend it either and
sometimes you have to work around them
so that's the only place where I see
that that's really an issue and that's
really only a regulatory issue it's not
really about performance or safety
issues per se no since they're how
important this static code analysis I
thought ADA had the property of being
more or less analyzable so that you
could look at or analyze the code with
tools and prove certain properties I
think it's probably more the case that
this is done on model level these days
so it's not that important that the
language actually is of actually
surpassed that right well access time
Sunita
it's nobody no better no worse than C++
okay all right I mean it's me so using
references the Thanks and showing us the
things then you have the issues of in
direct and indirect implications so yeah
if you stay away from them you can say
we're gonna see to what you say we from
them in C++ you can also stay away from
eeeh
yeah so it depends when you put the
things on the stack we put a lot of heat
okay Suzie's pointers you typically
using things on the on the heap right
and if anything Java the PUD worse
because everything goes on the heap the
driver
yeah but but not in Java right okay not
in real time job I think there is
there'sthere's ways to to well because
there are two different real time Javas
okay one has a kind of a wart on the
side of a normal virtual machine that's
the G consortium Java for the real time
stuff and one has a completely different
VM which has stuff that's more
deterministic but nevertheless I'm doing
is really using either two really great
three
but nevertheless the the issue of
analyzable means that you you just have
to be able to trace the values of these
function players and the problem bugs on
stack and oliver's if you don't know at
the point that you're doing Alice's what
the values of these pointers are if they
can change right but if you set them up
you can use patterns for you for example
you do your Cree dynamic creation of the
objects but only at the startup and you
ever delete anything right it's one of
the ways that people build relatively
simple real-time systems memory that's
been analyzable right they know our
currency ation with the values of all
the points are it's no different than
having a reference there's an address
did you call it a function when they
dynamically change that it's a little
bit different again wasn't things are
really excited me to find so so the
current state of tools may not be over
statically analyze it very well but
really fundamentally it should be
statically analyzable so let's briefly
look at the real-time operating systems
how are they different from general
purpose operating systems I guess one
thing is predictable scheduling well the
scheduling can be different that's only
one aspect you also tend to be more
scalable because there in Windows you
can we scale down so well I mean you get
what you get and don't don't give you
some of those but the generally speaking
they have mechanisms in place to do not
only breed monotonic scheduling she
detectable scheduling growth and
resource management again processing is
on but they really are own underneath
just kind of minimalist operating
systems they don't have necessarily all
the networking stuff you might find you
know and it just stop every so suppose
we do sometimes
that or a leaf is not a component with a
tend to be a bit more configurable back
right men or more compatible
okay so let's briefly look at some of
the best practices for building
real-time systems
one thing that I've think heard
somewhere is that you always try to
isolate the real-time part to a small
very small kernel and make all the non
time critical stuff more or less outside
put that outside the kernel
I guess that's that's a good idea to
keep the complexity of the of the
real-time issues as small as possible
actually I haven't seen that what I
think critical aspects are isolated okay
real-time aspects or not for example I
worked on anesthesia system once where
we had a bunch of stuff which we were
doing distributed control loops doing
some exclusive control and that part had
to be real-time that was done with the
vxworks eye watering system and that was
done with the critical aspects it was
actually closed up controlled delivery
of of therapy and these drugs there the
other stuff there's a bunch of stuff
around assisting the doctors to make
good decisions by adding dull kind of
graphical views and so on which was not
teaching criticals because it was just
an assist right we put that stuff
isolated away on an empty machine at
this time just different so it seems to
critical aspects that's certainly thing
out by the way but usually it's someone
decided to do real-time and once they
gonna run multiple computers doing
outside of the system
okay so you mentioned already the the
distribution challenge
what what what gets more difficult and
how do you handle if you have to build a
distributed a distributed real-time
system so somehow that the timing
constraints have to be well enforced
over multiple machines and over networks
and buses and all that stuff well the
fundamental there are two fundamental
problems with distributing systems right
one is that networks are inherently
unreliable as opposed to just running on
a computer
yeah generally speaking the send a
message to another thing on the same
computer it always gets there right you
never lose it unless you're running
Windows but the other one you never lose
it right
the Sunnis distribute there is lost
because of noise dropouts whatever
there's no loss and it's omits orders of
magnitude more often so that's that's
one of the primary aspects you really
have to consider when you're shooting
systems the other thing is that well
it's it's somewhere else and so that
takes time and effort you have to go
through more software protocol sacks I
can send the message or using a shared
memory or something like that if so some
more elaborate means to collaborate so
instead of just invoking a function or
referring off a deal if they hear munch
on this I have to send much more
information because they're not in the
same neighborhood right so they can't do
the same shortcuts but I can do and so
somehow I have to communicate that and
the way we do this is over wires or
over-the-air with communication
protocols so now that opens up a whole
can of worms if you will for an
opportunity to make mistakes to
distribute things across and then
depending upon the nature of the
communication channel and the political
views it can be deterministic agree
non-deterministic for example Ethernet
you think that saturates at about 30
percent load and what that means is
because it's a it's a collision
detecting system when you get a
collision you have to back off and we
retry at random times so it's 30 percent
load you're spending all your time
resolving collisions and really
essentially none of your time actually
getting data across as opposed to
something like a can bus which is a
priority based scheme not based on the
first 11 bits or twenty nine bits by
which version of candidate eating a bus
you have a priority scheme so if
somebody detects that it's called a bit
dominance game where if you right above
a bit out what's called sub dominant bit
and you read regression without on the
bus if it's not what you wrote someone
else is also kind of master bus and they
win because they put other dominant then
you put out a sub dominant and so in
that sense it's much more predictable
it's in depending upon the traffic that
that bus has to handle and the nature of
the Tumnus of that traffic
if you want to select one bus or network
over another one okay so final topic how
do I test real-time systems one thing
that you probably have heard about is
the Heisenberg we're trying to measure a
buck or debug something actually
actually influences what you want to
measure so this makes it quite
complicated I guess to to test and debug
rhythm systems oh yeah always fun well
basically the testing if it's on your
hips understand right off the bat you
can't test everything all right you have
to come up with a subset of the
functional path you can perhaps test all
static paths but when you soon as you
add in all data variants it's just an
essentially infinite set of data path
and control paths you have executed you
just can't do that no we couldn't we do
it set up your test into a said and I
only pause identify the federal kind of
test that you do such as functional test
and taken our values in the kind of
little for a particular functional path
use static path make sure all your all
your transitions your state machines is
the code level or the model level
dependable of analysis you want to do
you also do it can do statistical
testing where you do random samplings
across the distribution of your datasets
you can do boundary test we test right
around the boundaries things that are
invalid data out of valid data stress
testing volume testing where you you
know throw being at a higher rate than
you expect for longer than you expect to
have it you know those sorts of tests
when we come up with those tests and you
can either be a kind of code based
text-based approach or you can be model
based and Ivor again make a big believer
is moving from models as much as we can
so we were told of like test conductor
an EKG test conductor takes your
sequence diagrams you identify for your
use cases and uses them as test vectors
and this is one thing is anything it
really cool about the approach because
now you're capturing requirements and an
inherently testable way doesn't say
running a bunch of text describing and
then the TIF guys figure out what does
that mean and the bill pets forgot well
what does that mean you capture them
it's formal model artifacts
sequence diagrams and say this is where
expect to happen the developer knows
what's allowed to build against that and
the tensions of art that's what I need
to test against and took another tool
they can apply those tests automatically
and then you have tools like ATT out of
my test generator what that does is it
person's your model and make sure that
there's a test that covers everything
for example transition paths and state
machine branch pointing activity diagram
all your operations and actions get to
get Sally and that that sort of curb
assessing but the model level it's like
you so you get some assists you know
they gave a paper last year indicia that
the testing conference there and it was
pretty well received as what I had to
say about that so then that's kind of
how I believe personally you have to
identify the kind of since you want to
test whether this crest is long and
performance functional sarcastic
whatever and then come up with test
vectors and and you'll know actually
have facilities and then then those test
executors also allow you to monitor
timing event numbers distribution
deadlines missed and stuff so you can
actually test those timing problems now
I can there's an issue because yes you
pointed out - we had a point right as
soon as you modify something to measure
timing you modified it so its timing is
different and so what I marked you
argued for quite odd number years that
was really need to do with instrument
the ice heads so that it was completely
not an ASIS but interactive is difficult
because all these are nice vendors have
entirely different ways of representing
their data so in fact if it hasn't
hasn't happened but timing yeah you
typically use in circuit emulators you
use logic analyzers
you know Longley no no yeah I think use
the symbol table that's generated from
your compilers that apply I want to
start measure the size from here to here
or use markers and then you can use your
civil scopes and really the time between
you know something like that that's what
I've done and it's a pain yeah but I
have to use the hard part of testing is
the performance birthing include a black
box it's not so bad but then if you feel
box test then identifying in which point
is so you take some investigation this
is why I try to obviate the test as much
as I can and so they talked earlier
about the performance parameters I gave
obviously into the load test the
functions the method the actions and so
on that propagated down Louisville
performance budget so that when I tested
in isolation I'm relatively assured that
I'm gonna put them all together they've
all met their performance your
propagated performance budget their
their overall performance measures met
yeah not really on
I don't think about say about that early
on when you do testing you you may not
have the actual target hard work yeah so
then you do what I do is I take some
some measure and in fact I might run
some section of code there's four or
five different sections of code on the
actual target and on my desktop together
performance ratio between two platforms
and then use that so if I expect twenty
milliseconds on the target and my
sentence only three times faster than my
target then I do I can by doing within
seven or eight milliseconds I'm on
target for the actual target right and
so there's that kind of testing can you
do even really really early to get some
warm and fuzzy feeling that you're on
the right track which you do not want to
do in my experience is waiting to the
end if they all god I hope it works
yeah the later you the later you test
the bigger is the black box you have to
kind of trust and yeah right and the
more difficult it is yeah okay so what
are you working on today what is your
professional hobby these days what
fascinates you what are you playing with
well I'm the last book I wrote which was
the real time you know workshop and out
now for a few months and that's doing
very well and this you know a both of
interest about that I run a website on
Yahoo real time UML that has some some
discussions of related topics I'm doing
an awful lot of consulting as I
mentioned I'm doing this a helicopter
that I work in in Canada but I know I'm
in Europe I'm consulting to place in the
in Turkey for example I'm talking to the
Korea doing a bunch of designs
taking a lot of my time what are the
interesting things that I'm doing you
know with the Harmony process I'm
actually capturing this now in a process
authoring tool called EPF an eclipse
process framework and so that will be
released in a little over a month at
least in beta form and so that sounds
pretty cool because now we can generate
these would be a would sites of process
information which we cheated when we go
in we do I think on RDP we're at the
deployment and alchemy an or whether my
staff will come in and we create do we
take kind of the base material to create
a custom process depending on their
projects or business model business
culture the people involved we kind of
customize it for them and previously
this has been captured in Word document
like a handbook a guideline set of
guidelines either to do their work and
now we're going to be able to customize
this entire website for them until
hosted on their platform and that's
really really cool it's a lot of
interest in that there's been a lot of
my time and effort doing that another
thing that I was going on is a you PDM
the you know you know profile for dota
emotive that was just adopted last week
looking to adopt in the OMG oh my god
let it go to adopt so there's still some
some work need to be done on it there's
voted to a doctor last week and me in
Brussels that was good news so I was
working with that I will field the doing
that profile for Rhapsody so and that's
that's doing well but now we need to rev
it to be consistent and complying with
do they have 1.5 which is relief in
April this year as well no no no that's
is what do doubt it's a department
defense architecture framework okay
and as a finished version of it called
mograph the ministry of defense
architecture framework and it's a bunch
of kind of related standards on this is
one called naff to need no architecture
framework there's a bunch of kind of
related standards for that effort so
doing a lot of work with respect to that
and also now incorporating kind of the
SOA
technology everybody has enterprise
architectures yeah yeah okay is there
anything I forgot to ask you something
you want to
say before we wrap this up no I'm
excited to be a part of the industry
it's a very cool time you sound very how
to say very excited and very involved so
that's well I'd never get up in the
morning and say oh god I will show you
something to do yeah I wasn't allowed to
do and it wasn't really cool things
about my my job my life is that I got to
travel to all kinds of people doing all
kinds of things from secure radios to
cat scanners or you to embedded micro
devices so phone's GPS and find out what
they're doing how they're being
effective and kind of learn from that
and a fifth been developing all that
yeah okay Bruce then I thank you very
much for for being on the show I thought
it was very very interesting I hope our
listeners agree to that and thank you
very much for being on the show welcome
man
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio dotnet
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning Poli for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license
see the software engineering radio
website for details